Guide to the Gabriel Ersler Papers and Photographs ALBA.198
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Gabriel Ersler Papers and Photographs
1937-1987
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Ersler, Gabriel
ALBA.198
0.5 Linear Feet (1 box)
Dr. Gabriel Ersler (1913-2005) was born in Woclawek, Poland and studied medicine in Berlin and in Bern, Switzerland. He went to Spain in 1937 and became a staff doctor at the Centre de Instruccion de Madrigueras, Albacete. He then became chief of the medical unit of the 13th International Brigade. As an exile in France after the Spanish Civil War he joined the anti-fascist Resistance. In 1956 he moved from the Soviet Union back to his native Poland, where he became disillusioned by the resurgence there of anti-semitism and, in 1968, emigrated to France. By the 1970s he was living in Israel and practicing there as an eye specialist; during this period he also embarked on a major research project to create a biographical directory of foreign (and especially Jewish) volunteers in the medical units of the International Brigades. He published articles on the medical service in several languages, sometimes as G. E. Sichon or Gabriel Ersler Sichon, incorporating his mother's maiden name in the Spanish style. The collection contains a copy of extracts from Dr. Ersler's Notebook, kept in Spain, in 1937-1939; some souvenir items of stationery from Civil War-era Spain; copies of lists of International Brigades volunteers; copies of articles by Ersler and others; and a file of correspondence between Ersler and ALBA archivist Victor Berch. Also included is a series of photographs taken by Ersler in Spain in 1937-1938.
Arrangement
The collection is organized in 2 series: I, Subject Files, 1937-1987; II, Photographs and Photo Inventory, 1937-1938 and Undated.
Series I is arranged alphabetically; Series II is arranged by photograph number.
Related Archival Material
ALBA collection at the Tamiment Library.
Access Restrictions
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Tamiment Library & Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives for more information and to schedule an appointment, tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu or 212-998-2630.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains a copy of extracts from Dr. Ersler's Notebook, kept in Spain, in 1937-1939; some souvenir items of stationery from Civil War-era Spain; copies of lists of International Brigades volunteers; copies of articles by Ersler and others; and a file of correspondence between Ersler and ALBA archivist Victor Berch. Also included is a series of photographs taken by Ersler in Spain in 1937-1938.
Provenance
Most of these materials were donated to the ALBA archive by Dr. Gabriel Ersler in 1973; some may have been sent in later years. Items were sent by mail (along with donations of related books), to archivist Victor Berch at Brandeis University. The Ersler Papers and Photographs came to New York University in January 2001 as part of the original acquisition of ALBA collections, formerly housed at Brandeis.
Historical/Biographical Note
Dr. Gabriel Ersler (1913-2005) was born in Woclawek, Poland and studied medicine in Berlin until 1933 and in Bern, Switzerland until 1936. He went to Spain in 1937 and became a staff doctor at the Centre de Instruccion de Madrigueras, Albacete. He then became chief of the medical unit of the 13th International Brigade. As an exile in France after the Spanish Civil War he joined the anti-fascist Resistance. In 1956 he moved from the Soviet Union back to his native Poland, where he became disillusioned by the resurgence there of anti-semitism and, in 1968, emigrated to France. By the 1970s he was living in Israel and practicing there as an eye specialist. He traveled widely in Europe with his first wife, Conchita; after her death he married again, to Janine Szurek, and lived in his later years in France.
He embarked on a major research project to create a biographical directory of foreign (and especially Jewish) volunteers in the medical units of the International Brigades. In the course of this work he corresponded with, and eventually visited, Fredericka Martin, who was carrying out related research from her home in Cuernavaca, Mexico. He also corresponded with Victor Berch, archivist of the Lincoln Brigades collections at Brandeis University. Ersler published articles on the medical service in several languages, sometimes as G. E. Sichon or Gabriel Ersler Sichon, incorporating his mother's maiden name in the Spanish style.
- Series I: Subject Files, 1937-1987.
  Scope and Content Note
  Contains a copy of extracts from Dr. Ersler's Notebook, kept in Spain, 1937-1939; some souvenir items of stationery from Civil War-era Spain; copies of lists of International Brigades volunteers; copies of articles by Ersler and others; and a file of correspondence between Ersler and ALBA archivist Victor Berch.
  - Articles on the Medical Service in Spain, by G. Ersler and Others, from Ochotnik Wolnosci(in Polish; photostats and photocopies), Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence between GE and Victor Berch, 1973-1983 (Box 1, Folder 1A)
  - Extracts from a Notebook Kept by G. Ersler in Spain (typescript copy; in Polish), Dec 1937-Feb 1939 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Gohke, Dr. Nikolis, "Moja lekarska iskustva u spanskom ratu," from Vojnosanitetski Pregled (Yugoslavia, photocopy), 1967 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - List of Czechoslovakian Jewish Volunteers, Compiled by Union des Anciens Resistants Juife de Belgique, Undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Lists of Jewish Volunteers of Various Nationalities (photocopies, from several sources, in Polish, French, and Hebrew), 1967-1987 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Sichon, G. E. [G. Ersler], "Eliasz Hilsenrad -- 'Maciek Techniczek'" (typescript in Polish; with excerpts from two other essays or comments), 1989 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Sichon, G. E. [G. Ersler], "Polonais, d'origine juive, volontaires de la guerre civil en Espagne, 1936-1939" (typescript, with related notes), Undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Souvenir Stationery (Hospital/Clinic) and a Blank Postcard, from Spain, [1936-1939] (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Series II: Photographs and Photo Inventories, 1937-1938 and Undated.
  Contains black and white prints of photographs taken in Spain by Ersler, labeled with his original photograph numbers, and an inventory compiled by Victor Berch from Ersler's caption information. Ersler explains the history of these photographs in his letter to Berch of February 9, 1973 (in Folder 1A, above).
  - "Catalogue of Photographs Pertaining to the Spanish Civil War Presented to the Brandeis University Library by Dr. Gabriel Ersler, Israel," compiled by Victor Berch, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Hospital at Mataro [P. 1], Oct 9, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Departure of the International Brigades: 13th Dombrowski Brigade (includes Eugeniusz Szyr ("Misza", "Misza Reger", "Gerszon") and Franciszek "Franek" Ksiezarczyk) [P. 2], Sep 1938 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Depart of the 35th Division (includes Andre Marty, Luigi Longo ("Gallo"), and Col. Pedro Mateo Merino) + negative [P. 3], undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Group: Aragon "Retreats" (includes Lt. Otto, Erwin Kornell (Irving), Franciszek "Franek" Ksiezarczyk, and Dr. Stanislaw Flato) [P. 4], undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Group: Virgilio, Epiphanio "Emilio" Lopez, and Kazimierz Kozak [P. 5], undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Group: Lt. Valls, Dr. Sully Josef Brill, Dr. Leon Marcovic [P. 6], undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Nicolas [Skepastiotis?], Greek-American Ambulance Driver [P. 7], undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Group: Kirczenbaum, Seweryn "Sewek" and Dr. Gabriel "Gabrys" Ersler with two unidentified men (13th Brigade) [P. 8], undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Group: Kotlarz, Ignacy, Boleslaw Molojec ("Edward"), Stanislaw "Stasiek" Kubacki, Wiktor Mencel and others unidentified (13th International Brigade) [P. 9], undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Group: Molojec, Boleslaw ("Edward"), Ignacy Kotlarz, and others unidentified (Thirty Members of the 13th International Brigade) [P. 10], undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Ersler, Dr. Gabriel ("Gabrys") and Dr. Henryk Sternhell ("Gustaw") [P. 11], undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Winter, Dr. Kurt and Dr. Henryk Sternhell ("Gustaw") [P. 12], undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Group: Brill, Dr. Sully Josef, Henryk "Heniek" Torunczyk, and Dr. Gabriel "Gabrys" Ersler (Battle of Ebro) [P. 13], undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Broniatowski, Mieczyslaw [P. 14], undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Melchior, Maria "Maryska" [P. 15], undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Spira, Jozef [P. 16], undated [1938?] (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Lewinski, Adam (Ebro) [P. 17], undated [1938?] (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Pietrzak, Antoni "Antek" [P. 18], undated [1938?] (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Szyr, Eugeniusz ("Misza", "Misza Reger", "Gerszon") [P. 19], Autumn 1938 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Mora, Luciano [P. 20], undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Rutkowski, Szymon [P. 21], undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Warszawski, Chaim [P. 22], undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Torunezyk, Henryk "Heniek" [P. 23], undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Von Golsenau, Arnold ("Ludwig Renn") [P. 24], undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Group: Kirszenbaum, Seweryn "Sewek" and two others unidentified (Aragon "retreats") [P. 25], undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Kirszenbaum, Seweryn "Sewek" [P. 26], undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Buchholc, Zbigniew "Zbyszek" [P. 27], undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Group: Pinto, Dr. Rocha Pinto (Indian radiologist) and Dr. Gabriel "Gabrys" Ersler [P. 28], undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Group: Marcovic, Dr. Leon, Dr. Gabriel "Gabrys" Ersler, and Dr. Valls (Spanish lieutenant in medical corps.) [P. 29], undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Group: Ersler, Dr. Gabriel "Gabrys" and nurse Maria "Maryska" Melchior (includes negative) [P. 30], undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Group: Molojec, Boleslaw "Edward" and Franciszek "Franek" Ksiezarczyk [P. 31], undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Group: Bachrach, Dr. Jakub "Kuba" and unidentified dentist [P. 32], undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Group: Deutscher, Henryk, Chaim Jungman ("Janusz Jurkowski"), Hercel Orzech ("Olek", aka Aleksander Nus), unidentified Russian motorcyclist, Dr. Matis Scheinberg, Dr. Gabriel "Gabrys" Ersler [P. 33] (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Group: Torunczyk, Henryk "Heniek", Chaim Jungman ("Janusz Jurkowski"), Kharchenko, Martinez (Mikhail E. "Kharchenko") [P. 34], undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Group: Kozak, Kazimierz, Virgilio, and Dr. Gabriel "Gabrys" Ersler next to 13th Brigade ambulance [P. 35], undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Group: Twenty Volunteers, unidentified [P. 36], undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Group: Company of Volunteers, unidentified [P. 37], undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Wall Poster: "Dos anos Servicio Sanitario Internacional" [P. 38], undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - "Official" departure speech by Juan Negrin to the International Brigades [P. 39], undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Group: Molojec, Zygmunt, Julian Kirchner, Franciszek "Franek" Ksiezarczyk, and others unidentified [P. 40], undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - 13th Brigade Soldiers and Aragon civilians clear road (includes Maria "Maryska" Melchior) [P. 41], undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - 13th Brigade clearing road [P. 42], undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Dr. Sternhell taking a group photograph (includes Dr. Henryk Sternhell and Dr. Herbert Gabe) [P. 43], undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Group: Molojec, Boleslaw "Edward" with 13th Brigade staff [P. 44], undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Group: Molojec, Boleslaw "Edward", Dr. Gabriel "Gabrys" Ersler, and unidentified sergeant [P. 45], undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Group: 13th Brigade Cavalry (unidentified) [P. 46], undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Group: Hahn, Dr. Geza, "Carmelito", Dr. Matis Scheinberg, Dr. Gabriel "Gabrys" Ersler, and others unidentified [P. 47], undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Entrance to International Brigade Hospital (Mataro) [P. 48], undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Field Hospital (Battle of the Ebro) [P. 49], undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Field Hospital (Battle of the Ebro) [P. 50], undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Group: Flato, Dr. Stanislaw, Dr. S. Brill, Dr. Juan ("Juanto"), and others unidentified [P. 51], April 1938 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Group: Kotlarz, Ignacy, Franciszek "Franek" Ksiezarczyk, Zygmunt Molojec, Szlama Warszawski [P. 52], undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Group: Medical Personnel of 1st (Dombrowski) Battalion during Aragon retreat and the Battle of the Ebro [P. 53], undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Group: Ersler, Dr. Gabriel "Gabrys", Dr. Matis Scheinberg, and others unidentified [P. 54], undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Group: Khvatov, Mikhail E. "Kharchenko" and other officials of the 13th International Brigade [P. 55], undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Group: Abramowicz, David, Jerzy Braun, Warszawski [P. 56], undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Sternhell, Dr. Henryk ("Gustaw") [P. 57], undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Group: Ersler, Dr. Gabriel "Gabrys", Valls, Dr. Leon Marcovic, and others unidentified [P. 58], Apr 28, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Group: Medical Staff, Dr. Sully Josef Brill and Dr. "Juanito" [P. 59], undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Group: Medical Staff, Dr. "Juanito", Dr. Sully Josef Brill, Dr. Stanislaw Flato [P. 60], undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Group: Pietrzak, Antoni ("Antek"), Jan "Szymon" Rutkowski, Emile Warme [P. 61], undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Brill, Dr. Sully Josef [P. 62], undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Group: Brill, Dr. Sully Josef, Dr. Bachrach, Dr. Henryk Sternhell ("Gustaw") [P. 63], undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Group: Brill, Dr. Sully Josef, Dr. Jakub "Kuba" Bachrach, Dr. Henryk Sternhell ("Gustaw") [P. 64], undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Group: Ersler, Dr. Gabriel "Gabrys" and Dr. Kurt Winter [P. 65], undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Group: Warme, Emile and other International Brigade members unidentified [P. 66], undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Group: Spira, Jozef, Jozef Mazel ("Jozef Sulinski"), Zbigniew "Zbyszek" Bucholc, Borkowski, and unidentified [P. 67], undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Group: Martinez, Lt. Leopold "Mily" Czerniak, Chaim Warzawski ("Jaime"), and unidentified [P. 68], undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Group: Josef Mrozek and Lt. Leopold "Mily" Czerniak [P. 69], undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - New Volunteers of 13th Brigade (Aragon) [P. 70], 1938 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - 13th International Brigade Machine Gun Company [P. 71], undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Group: Longo, Luigi ("Gallo") and Andre Marty (includes negative) [P. 72], undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Group: Jaszunski, Salomon "Justyn", Andre Marty, Col. Pedro Mateo Merino, Commander Mikhail E. Khvatov ("Kharchenko"), and Luigi Longo ("Gallo") [P. 73], undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Officials visit International Brigades before the Battle of the Ebro (includes Luigi Longo ("Gallo") and Andre Marty) [P. 74], undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Pontoon Bridge (Ebro) [P. 75], Jul 25, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Group: Torunczyk, Henryk "Heniek", Franciszek "Franek" Ksiezarczyk, Boleslaw "Edward" Molojec, and others unidentified [P. 76], Spring 1938 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Group: Medical Post, Dr. Henryk Sternhell ("Gustaw") and Dr. Herbert Gabe [P. 77], Jul 30, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Group: Medical Staff, Dr. "Carmelito", Dr. Henryk Sternhell, Luciano Mora, Dr. Gabriel "Gabrys" Ersler, Dr. Herbert Gabe, and Dr. Geza Hahn [P. 78], undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Wall of 13th International Brigade Medical Unit [P. 79], undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Medical Post of 13th International Brigade [P. 80], [1938?] (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - 13th International Brigade crossing the Ebro [P. 81], Jul 25, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Dombrowski Battalion [P. 82], undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Group: 13th International Brigade Staff examining bombardment effects [P. 83], undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Sternhell, Dr. Henryk ("Gustaw") and Alejandro Bea [P. 84], Spring or Summer 1938 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Group: Melchior, Maria "Maryska", Dr. S. Flato, and A. Bea [P. 85], undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Group: Infantry Battalion "Rakosi" (includes 3 unidentified individuals) [P. 86], undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - 13th International Brigade (includes "Rakosi" Battalion) [P. 87], Oct 15, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Pontoon Bridge across Ebro (includes copy negative) [P. 88], Jul 25, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Dombrowski Battalion "Fiesta" [P. 89], Jun 11, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Dombrowski Battalion "Fiesta" (includes Spanish children) [P. 90], Jun 11, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Machine Gunners (includes Stefan Szelest) [P. 91], Sep 22, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Captured Spanish Aviator [P. 92], undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Group: Molojec, Boleslaw "Edward", Henryk "Heniek" Torunczyk, Mihaly "Tchapaiev" Salvai, and others unidentified [P. 93], Summer 1938 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - "Rakosi" Battalion Parade (includes Mihaly "Tchapaiev" Salvai) [P. 94], undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Observation Post on the Ebro [P. 95], May 1, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Group: Rutkowski, Jan "Szymon" and Emile Warme [P. 96], May 9, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - International Brigades: Parade Formation [P. 97], Oct 15, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Bulletin Board (results of a shooting match) [P. 98], Jun 1938 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Women's delegation from Barcelona visit the 13th International Brigade [P. 99], Jun 11, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Dombrowski Battalion during Aragon "retreats" [P. 100], 1938 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Group: Ersler, Dr. Gabriel "Gabrys" and Dr. Matis Scheinberg [P. 101], May 16, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Destroy Bridge (Asco) [P. 102], undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Departure of International Brigades from the Spanish Army (includes Andre Marty and Luigi Longo ("Gallo")) [P. 103], undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Departure of International Brigades (13th Brigade, includes Franciszek "Franek" Ksiezarczyk and Eugeniusz Szyr ("Misza", "Misza Reger", "Gerszon")) [P. 104], undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Departure of International Brigades (includes copy negative) [P. 105], undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Departure of International Brigades (includes Dr. Gabriel "Gabrys" Ersler) [P. 106], undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Stretcher Bearers of 13th International Brigade (includes Alejandro Bea, Luciano Mora, and Dr. Gabriel "Gabrys" Ersler) [P. 107], undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Group: Sternhell, Dr. Henryk with unidentified officer (Aragon "retreats") [P. 108], undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Group: "Mio" and Stefan Szelest, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - 13th International Brigade first aid and stretcher bearers (drill exercises) [P. 110], May 1938 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Medical Company Flag (13th International Brigade) [P. 111], undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - First-Aid Men and Stretcher Bearers (drill exercises) [P. 112], undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Medical Company (13th International Brigade) [P. 113], undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Medical Company (13th International Brigade) [P. 114], undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Medical Company (13th International Brigade) [P. 115], undated (Box 1, Folder 21)